A Guide to the Abraham Pais papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA014
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Pais Photos, 1920-1997; 7; 1.5 Cubic Feet
  - Glass Slides - Pi Meson - Table IV, undated (Box 86, Folder 29)
  - Glass Slides - The Rockefeller University #1, undated (Box 86, Folder 30)
  - Glass Slides - The Rockefeller University #2, undated (Box 86, Folder 31)
  - Glass Slides - The Rockefeller University #3, undated (Box 86, Folder 32)
  - Glass Slides - The Rockefeller University #4, undated (Box 86, Folder 33)
  - Glass Slides - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #1, undated (Box 86, Folder 34)
  - Glass Slides - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #2, undated (Box 86, Folder 35)
  - Glass Slides - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #3, undated (Box 86, Folder 36)
  - Glass Slides - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #4, undated (Box 86, Folder 37)
  - Glass Slides - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #5, undated (Box 86, Folder 38)
  - Glass Slides - Table 1 - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #1, undated (Box 86, Folder 39)
  - Glass Slides - Table 1 - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #2, undated (Box 86, Folder 40)
  - Glass Slides - Table 1 - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #3, undated (Box 86, Folder 41)
  - Glass Slides - Table 1 - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #4, undated (Box 86, Folder 42)
  - Glass Slides - Table 1 - States & Classes of N pi-Clouds #5, undated (Box 86, Folder 43)
- Reprints, 1941-1999; 8; 1.6 Cubic Feet
  This series contains pre-prints and reprints of articles by Abraham Pais both individually and as part of a collaboration. The series also contains reprints and pre-prints by colleagues of Pais. These have been either autographed or annotated in some form.
  - Angular Correlations in K - Decay Processes, 1957 (Box 87, Folder 1)
  - Approximate Unitary Symmetry and the Parity Question, 1964 (Box 87, Folder 2)
  - [The] Behavior of Neutral Particles under Charge Conjunction, 1955 (Box 87, Folder 3)
  - Calculability and Naturalness in Gauge Theories - 135, 1974 (Box 87, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 2 - Introducing Atoms and Their Nuclei, undated (Box 87, Folder 5)
  - Charge Independence and Multiple Pion Production, 1952 (Box 87, Folder 6)
  - Charmed-Meson Lifetime Ratios and Production in e[^+]-e[^-] Collisions - 149, 1977 (Box 87, Folder 7)
  - Classical Example of Essentially Singular Coupling, 1964 (Box 87, Folder 8)
  - A Class of Gauge Theories with Superweak CP Violation - 130, 1973 (Box 87, Folder 9)
  - Colliding Electron Versus Colliding Photon Beams - Comments on Nuclear and Particle Physics - 119, 1972 (Box 87, Folder 10)
  - Comment on Nonleptonic Decays of Charmed Hadrons - 139, 1975 (Box 87, Folder 11)
  - Comments on Hadronic Helicity Conservation in Inelastic Lepton-Nuclean Reactions - 120, 1971 (Box 87, Folder 12)
  - Comments on the Production and Decay of Charged Heavy Leptons - 147, 1976 (Box 87, Folder 13)
  - Correlations Between Cusps in Differential Cross Sections and in Polarizations, 1961 (Box 87, Folder 14)
  - CP Violation in Charged-Particle Decays - 142, 1975 (Box 87, Folder 15)
  - CP Violations and Electric Dipole Moments in Gauge Theories of Weak Interactions - 132, 1973 (Box 87, Folder 16)
  - CP Violation as a Quantum Effect - 137, 1974 (Box 87, Folder 17)
  - De Broglie, Einstein, and the Birth of the Matter Wave Concept, undated (Box 87, Folder 18)
  - De Huidige Stand van Het Pariteitsprobleem en van Het Tijdsomkeerprobleem, 1957 (Box 87, Folder 19)
  - Developments in the Theory of the Electron - 14, 1948 (Box 87, Folder 20)
  - The Discovery of the Electron - "Beam Line" (Stanford Linear Accelerator Center), 1997 (Box 87, Folder 21)
  - Dynamical Asymmetry in Octet Space - Nobel Symposium 8: Elementary Particle Theory: Relativistic Groups and Analyticity - 108, undated (Box 87, Folder 22)
  - Dynamical Symmetry in Particle Physics - 97, 1966 (Box 87, Folder 23)
  - The Early History of the Theory of the Electron: 1897-1947, 1972 (Box 87, Folder 24)
  - Einstein and the Press - "Physics Today", 1994 (Box 87, Folder 25)
  - Einstein, Newton, and Success - Einstein, A Centenary Volume - 154, 1979 (Box 87, Folder 26)
  - Electromagnetic Effects on Decays of G Eigenstates, 1962 (Box 87, Folder 27)
  - Electromagnetic Mass, undated (Box 87, Folder 28)
  - Electron - 146, 1981 (Box 87, Folder 29)
  - Energy Bounds for Charm and for Heavy Lepton Production in e[^+]-e[^-] Annihilation - 148, 1976 (Box 87, Folder 30)
  - The Energy Momentum Tenso in Projective Relativity Theory, 1941 (Box 87, Folder 31)
  - Fachbericht ber schwache Wechselwirkungen - 88, undated (Box 87, Folder 32)
  - A Field Theory of Weak Interactions. I. - 70, 1963 (Box 87, Folder 33)
  - A Field Theory of Weak Interactions. II. - 75, 1964 (Box 87, Folder 34)
  - Fluctuations of the Charged Pion Number in e[^+]-e[^-] Annihilation - 138, 1974 (Box 87, Folder 35)
  - 4. Complex Octorions, undated (Box 87, Folder 36)
  - Gauge Theories and "Elastic" Weak Neutral Currents - 133, 1974 (Box 87, Folder 37)
  - Gauge Theories: How Does It Stand? - 145, 1975 (Box 87, Folder 38)
  - A General Transformation of the Symmetrical Pseudoscalar Theory, 1959 (Box 87, Folder 39)
  - Generalization of the Glashow-Illiopoulos-Maiani Mechanism: Horizontal and Vertical Flavor Mixing - 155, 1979 (Box 87, Folder 40)
  - George E. Uhlenbeck (December 6, 1900-October 31, 1988), 1989 (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - Glimpses of Oskar Klein as Scientist and Thinker, 1994 (Box 88, Folder 2)
  - Hadronic Helicity Conservation and Inelastic Lepton - Nucleon Reactions - 118, 1971 (Box 88, Folder 3)
  - Het Institute for Advanced Study, undated (Box 88, Folder 4)
  - Higher Symmetries (Erice) - 96, 1966 (Box 88, Folder 5)
  - How Can We Verify the Weak Selection Rules of the New Particles? - 150, 1977 (Box 88, Folder 6)
  - How Einstein Got the Nobel Prize - "American Scientist" - 161, 1982 (Box 88, Folder 7)
  - How Many Charm Quantum Numbers Are There? - 144, 1975 (Box 88, Folder 8)
  - The Impact of Einstein's Relativity Theory, 1988 (Box 88, Folder 9)
  - Implications of Spin-Unitary Spin Independence, 1964 (Box 88, Folder 10)
  - The Impossible Real, 1993 (Box 88, Folder 11)
  - Influence of Bose-Einstein Statistics on the Antiproton-Proton Annihilation Process, 1960 (Box 88, Folder 12)
  - In Memoriam: Robert Serber (1909-1997), 1999 (Box 88, Folder 13)
  - Interaction Between K-Particles and Nucleons, 1955 (Box 88, Folder 14)
  - Invariance Principles, 1963 (Box 88, Folder 15)
  - Invariance Principles, 1968 (Box 88, Folder 16)
  - Isabelle Physics Prospects - 128, 1972 (Box 88, Folder 17)
  - Isospin Constraints on Semi-Inclusive Neutrino Reactions and Their Hadronic Analogs - 124, 1972 (Box 88, Folder 18)
  - Isotopic Spin and Mass Quantization, 1953 (Box 88, Folder 19)
  - Kernfysica in Nederland: de beginjaren - "nederlands tijdschrift voor natuurkunde", 1991 (Box 88, Folder 20)
  - Lepton Pairings in the Two-Neutrino Theory - 57, 1961 (Box 88, Folder 21)
  - Life-time of the Neutral Meson, 1945 (Box 88, Folder 22)
  - Light-Cone Approach to Structure-Functions Inequalities - 125, 1972 (Box 88, Folder 23)
  - Low-Energy Theorems and Internal Symmetry - 99, 1967 (Box 88, Folder 24)
  - Low-Energy Theorems for Spin [> or =] 1 - 101, 1967 (Box 88, Folder 25)
  - The Many pi-Meson Problem - 52, 1960 (Box 88, Folder 26)
  - The Many pi-Meson Problem II - 68, 1963 (Box 88, Folder 27)
  - Max Born's Statistical Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics - "Science" - 163, 1982 (Box 88, Folder 28)
  - Meson Fields in Projective Space, 1942 (Box 88, Folder 29)
  - Methods and Problems in the Dynamics of Weak Interactions, 1963 (Box 88, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Reprints, 1955-1993 (Box 88, Folder 31)
  - Natural Stepwise Breaking of Gauge and Discrete Symmetries - 151, 1977 (Box 88, Folder 32)
  - Niels Bohr and the Development of Physics, 1988 (Box 88, Folder 33)
  - Note on Relations Between Baryon-Meson Coupling Constraints, 1958 (Box 89, Folder 1)
  - Note on Relations Between Baryon-Meson Coupling Constraints, 1958 (Box 89, Folder 2)
  - Note on Relativistic Properties of Self-Energies, 1949 (Box 89, Folder 3)
  - Note on the Decay and Absorption of the theta°†, 1955 (Box 89, Folder 4)
  - Note on the Theory of Vector Wave Fields, 1946 (Box 89, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Antibaryon Interactions, 1959 (Box 89, Folder 6)
  - Notes on W[subscript 3] and Related Symmetries, 1964 (Box 89, Folder 7)
  - Neutral Heavy Leptons as a Source for Di-muon Events: A Criterion - 143, 1975 (Box 89, Folder 8)
  - Nuclear Physics in the Netherlands, the Early Years - AIK (Vrije Universiteit te Amsterdam), 1990 (Box 89, Folder 9)
  - Neutral-Current Effects in a Class of Gauge Field Theories - 127, 1972 (Box 89, Folder 10)
  - Observations on the Isostructure of Currents - 123, 1972 (Box 89, Folder 11)
  - On a Plane Ising Lattice with First and Second Interactions - 69, 1963 (Box 89, Folder 12)
  - On High Energy Nucleon-Nucleon Scattering, 1950 (Box 89, Folder 13)
  - On Spin-Orbit Interactions and Nucleon-Nucleon Scattering, 1950 (Box 89, Folder 14)
  - On Spinors in eta Dimensions, 1962 (Box 89, Folder 15)
  - On Symmetries Shared by Strong and Weak Interactions, 1960 (Box 89, Folder 16)
  - On Symmetries Shared by Strong and Weak Interactions, 1960 (Box 89, Folder 17)
  - On the Baryon-Meson-Photon System, 1953 (Box 89, Folder 18)
  - On the Dirac Theory of the Electron (1930-1936), 1989 (Box 89, Folder 19)
  - On the Electric Charge Current Density of a Nuclear System, 1942 (Box 89, Folder 20)
  - On the Gentle Art of Hunting Bumps in the Pion-Hyperon System, 1961 (Box 89, Folder 21)
  - On the Photo-Disintegration of the Deuteron, 1943 (Box 89, Folder 22)
  - On the Need for Higher Energies - Nature of Matter: Purposes of High Energy Physics - 90, undated (Box 89, Folder 23)
  - On the Program of a Systematization of Particles and Interactions, 1954 (Box 89, Folder 24)
  - On the Quantum Theory of the Third Virial Coefficient, 1959 (Box 89, Folder 25)
  - On the Scattering of a Particle by a Static Potential, 1951 (Box 89, Folder 26)
  - On the Scattering of Fast Neutrons by Protons, 1945 (Box 89, Folder 27)
  - On the Self-Energy of Mesons, 1946 (Box 89, Folder 28)
  - On the Theory of Elementary Particles, 1946 (Box 89, Folder 29)
  - On the Theory of Elementary Particles, 1947 (Box 89, Folder 30)
  - On the Theory of the Electron and the Neutron, 1945 (Box 89, Folder 31)
  - O(4) Treatment of the Electromagnetic-Weak Synthesis - 129, 1972 (Box 89, Folder 32)
  - Parity and Other Symmetries in Strong Interactions, 1958 (Box 89, Folder 33)
  - The Particle Jungle - "The Rockefeller University Review" - 98, 1966 (Box 89, Folder 34)
  - The Physical Review: Then and Now, undated (Box 89, Folder 35)
  - Physics After tau and T - High-Energy Physics in the Einstein Centennial Year -157, 1979 (Box 89, Folder 36)
  - Physics in the Making in Bohr's Copenhagen - Physics in the Making - 180, 1989 (Box 90, Folder 1)
  - "Pions to Quarks: Particle Physics in the 1950's" - From the 1940's into the 1950's, 1989 (Box 90, Folder 2)
  - Playing with Equations, the Dirac Way, 1987 (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Polarization Effects in Sigma Capture, 1958 (Box 90, Folder 4)
  - Possibility of Hyperfragment Formation in K[^-]-d Reactions, 1957 (Box 90, Folder 5)
  - The Power of the Word, 1995 (Box 90, Folder 6)
  - "The Princeton Period" - "Physics Today" - 103, 1967 (Box 90, Folder 7)
  - Program of Systematization of Particles and Interactions - 29, 1954 (Box 90, Folder 8)
  - Prong Inequalities for e[^+]-e[^-]--> gamma --> N pi - 136, 1974 (Box 90, Folder 9)
  - Properties and Effects of zeta Decays, 1962 (Box 90, Folder 10)
  - Radioactivity's Two Early Puzzles - Transactions of the New York Academy of Sciences - 152, 1977 (Box 90, Folder 11)
  - Radioactivity's Two Early Puzzles - 153, 1977 (Box 90, Folder 12)
  - Relative Parity of Charged and Neutral K-Particles, 1958 (Box 90, Folder 13)
  - Remark on Baryon Conservation - 131, 1973 (Box 90, Folder 14)
  - Remark on Energy Peaks in Meson Systems, 1962 (Box 90, Folder 15)
  - Remark on the Algebra of Interactions, 1961 (Box 90, Folder 16)
  - "Reminiscences from the Post-War Years" from "Niels Bohr: His Life and Work" - 73, 1967 (Box 90, Folder 17)
  - Res Jost, January 10, 1918-October 3, 1990, undated (Box 90, Folder 18)
  - Review: Physics, Life and the Mind - Symmetries and Reflections by Eugene P. Wigner - 102, 1967 (Box 90, Folder 19)
  - Scattering Formalism for Singular Potential Theory, 1964 (Box 90, Folder 20)
  - Scattering on High-Energy Neutrons by Protons, 1947 (Box 90, Folder 21)
  - The Scientific Work of T. D. Lee and C. N. Yang, 1958 (Box 90, Folder 22)
  - Selection Rules Imposed by Charge Conjugation and Charge Symmetry, 1952 (Box 90, Folder 23)
  - Semisimple Graded Lie Algebras - 141, 1975 (Box 90, Folder 24)
  - Singular Potentials and Peratization. I., 1964 (Box 90, Folder 25)
  - Singular Potentials and Peratization. II., 1964 (Box 90, Folder 26)
  - Some New Isospin Bounds in Multipion Production - 126, 1972 (Box 90, Folder 27)
  - Some Theoretical Aspects of Colliding e[^+]-e[^-] Beams - 122, 1971 (Box 90, Folder 28)
  - Source of Stability of the New Particles, 1955 (Box 90, Folder 29)
  - Speculations on CP-Invariance and the 2pi-Modes of Long-Lived Neutral K-Particles, undated (Box 90, Folder 30)
  - Spherical Spinors in Euclidean 4-Space - 30, 1954 (Box 90, Folder 31)
  - Spin and Unitary Spin Independence of Strong Interactions, 1964 (Box 90, Folder 32)
  - Strong Coupling, 1957 (Box 90, Folder 33)
  - The Structure of Matter - 71, undated (Box 90, Folder 34)
  - Symmetries of the Strong Interactions, 1958 (Box 90, Folder 35)
  - Theoretical Aspects of Nonleptonic Hyperon Decays - 54, 1961 (Box 90, Folder 36)
  - Theoretical Particle Physics, 1999 (Box 90, Folder 37)
  - Theoretical Views on the New Particles, undated (Box 90, Folder 38)
  - Theorem on Local Action of Lepton Currents, 1962 (Box 90, Folder 39)
  - Theta Quantum Chromodynamics Without Instantons - 160, 1981 (Box 90, Folder 40)
  - Three-Pion Decay Modes of Neutral K Mesons, 1957 (Box 90, Folder 41)
  - Twentieth Century Physics, 1995 (Box 90, Folder 42)
  - [Untitled Collection of Pais Reprints], 1961-1981 (Box 91, Folder 1)
  - Vacuum Symmetry and the Pseudo-Goldstone Phenomenon - 140, 1975 (Box 91, Folder 2)
  - Vertices with Partial SU(6,6) Structure - Preludes in Theoretical Physics - 95, 1966 (Box 91, Folder 3)
  - Weak Interactions - 65, 1961 (Box 91, Folder 4)
    (Solvay Report)
  - Weak Interactions at High Energies, 1963 (Box 91, Folder 5)
  - Weak Interactions at High Energies - 117, 1971 (Box 91, Folder 6)
  - Weak Interactions at High Energies - Theoretical Physics, 1963 (Box 91, Folder 7)
  - Weak Neutral Currents - 134, 1974 (Box 91, Folder 8)
  - What Happened in Copenhagen?: A Physicist's View and the Playwright's Response, 2000 (Box 91, Folder 9)
  - Woolly Cusps, 1962 (Box 91, Folder 10)
  - World War II and American Science, undated (Box 91, Folder 11)
  - omega-Space Theory, 1953 (Box 91, Folder 12)
  - Zwei ratselhafte Fragen aus der Frhzeit der Radioaktivitt - 159, 1980 (Box 91, Folder 13)
  - Calabi, Eugenio - "Construction and Properties of Some 6-Dimensional Almost Complex Manifolds", 1958 (Box 91, Folder 14)
  - Cartan, M. Elie - "Les Rcentes Gnralisations de la Notion D'Espace", undated (Box 91, Folder 15)
  - Freudenthal, Hans - "Lie Groups and Foundations of Geometry", 1959 (Box 91, Folder 16)
  - Freudenthal, Hans - "Oktaven, Ausnahmegruppen und Oktavengeometrie", 1951 (Box 91, Folder 17)
  - Jacobson, N. - "Composition Algebras and Their Automorphisms", 1958 (Box 91, Folder 18)
  - Jordan, P. - "Zur Axiomatischen Begrndung der Quantenmechanik", 1952 (Box 91, Folder 19)
  - Jost, Res W. - "Introduction la Thorie Quantique des Champs", undated (Box 91, Folder 20)
  - gmundsson, Vilhjlmur - "Multiplication in eta Dimensions", 1959 (Box 91, Folder 21)
  - Oppenheimer, J. R. - "Notes on Electrodynamics" - University of California, Physics 207B, 1939 - By S. Kusaka, with the Collaboration of S. Frankel and E. Nelson, 1947 (Box 91, Folder 22)
  - "Scientific American" (Collection of Reprints), 1948-1969 (Box 92, Folder 1)
  - Souriau, J. M. & D. Kastler - "Cayley Octonions and Strong Interactions" (Preprint), undated (Box 92, Folder 2)
  - Uhlenbeck, G. E. - "The Statistical Mechanics of Non-Equilibrium Phenomena", 1954 (Box 92, Folder 3)
  - Van Der Blij - "History of the Octaves", 1961 (Box 92, Folder 4)